For a moment, what I need to do
لبرهة, ما أريد عمله هو
is project something on the screen of your imagination.
عرض شيء على شاشة خيالكم
We're in 17th century Japan
نحن في اليابان في القرن السابع عشر
on the west coast,
على الساحل الغربي
and a little, wizened monk
هناك راهب ضئيل ذابل
is hurrying along, near midnight,
يسرع قرابة منتصف الليل
to the crest of a small hill.
إلى قمة تل صغير
He arrives on the small hill,
يصل إلى التل
dripping with water.
يقطر منه الماء
He stands there,
يقف هناك
and he looks across at the island, Sado.
وينظر عبر جزيرة سادو
And he scans across the ocean, and he looks at the sky.
يمسح بنظره المحيط , وينظر إلى السماء
Then he says to himself, very quietly,
عندها يقول لنفسه بهدوء بالغ
"[Turbulent the sea,]
البحر متمرد
[Stretching across to Sado]
متمددة عبر جزيرة سادو
[The Milky Way]."
مجرة درب التبانة
Basho was a brilliant man.
كان باشو عبقريا
He said more with less
قال الكثير عبر القليل
than any human
أكثر من أي إنسان
that I have ever read or talked to.
قرأت له أو تحدثت معه
Basho, in 17 syllables,
باشو في سبعة عشر بيتا
juxtaposed
وضع جنبا إلى جنب
a turbulent ocean
تمرد محيط
driven by a storm now past,
قادته عاصفة مضت
and captured the almost
ووصف الجمال
impossible beauty
شبه المستحيل
of our home galaxy
لمجرتنا
with millions of stars,
مع ملايين النجوم
probably hundreds and hundreds of -- who knows how many -- planets,
وربما المئات و المئات من الكواكب - لا أحد يعلم عددها-
maybe even an ocean
وربما حتى المحيط
that we will probably call Sylvia in time.
الذي غالبا ما سينادي "سيلفيا" مع مرور الزمن
As he was nearing his death,
لأنه كان يقترب من موته
his disciples and followers
ظل حواريوه وأتباعه
kept asking him,
يسألونه,
"What's the secret?
ما هو السر؟
How can you
كيف استطعت
make haiku poems so beautiful so easily?"
كتابة قصائد هايكو – نوع من القصائد اليابانية- بهذا الجمال بتلك السهولة؟
And toward the end, he said,
وقرابة النهاية, قال
"If you would know the pine tree,
"إذا أردت أن تعرف شجرة الصنوبر,
go to the pine tree."
فاذهب إلى شجرة الصنوبر"
That was it.
هذا كل ما قاله
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Sylvia has said we must use
قالت سيلفيا أنه يجب أن نستخدم
every capacity we have
كل القدرات التي نملكها
in order to know the oceans.
لمحاولة معرفة المحيط
If we would know the oceans,
لو أردنا أن نعرف المحيطات
we must go to the oceans.
يجب أن نذهب إلى المحيطات
And what I'd like to talk to you today about, a little bit,
وما أريد أن أحدثكم قليلا عنه اليوم
is really transforming
هو حقيقة تحويل
the relationship, or the interplay,
العلاقة أو التفاعل
between humans and oceans
بين البشر والمحيطات
with a new capability
بإمكانات جديدة
that is not at all routine yet.
لم تصبح معتادة بعد
I hope it will be.
أتمنى أن تصبح كذلك
There are a few key points.
هناك بضع نقاط مفتاحية
One of them is the oceans are central
إحداها أن المحيطات أساسية
to the quality of life on earth.
لجودة الحياة على الأرض
Another is that there are bold, new ways
وأخرى أنه هناك طرق جريئة وجديدة
of studying oceans
لدراسة المحيطات
that we have not used well yet.
لم نستخدمها بشكل جيد بعد
And the last is that these bold, new ways
والنقطة الأخيرة هي أن هذه الطرق الجريئة والجديدة
that we are exploring
التي نستكشفها
as a community
كمجتمع
will transform the way we look at our planet, our oceans,
ستغير طريقة نظرنا نحو كوكبنا ومحيطاتنا
and eventually how we manage
وفي نهاية المطاف كيف ندير
probably the entire planet, for what it's worth.
ربما كل الكوكب لما هو أهل له
So what scientists do when they begin
إذاً ما يفعله العلماء عندما يبدأون
is to start with the system.
هو البدء بالنظام
They define what the system is.
يعرّفون ما هو النظام
The system isn't Chesapeake Bay.
النظام ليس ساحل تشيزابيك (أكبر مصبات الأنهار في الولايات المتحدة)
It's not the Kuril arc. It's not even the entire Pacific.
وهو ليس قوس كارو ولا هو حتى المحيط الهادئ كله
It's the whole planet,
إنه الكوكب ككل
the entire planet, continents and oceans together.
كل الكوكب, القارات والمحيطات معا
That's the system.
هذا هو النظام
And basically, our challenge
وفي الأساس, تحدينا هو
is to optimize the benefits
رفع الفوائد لأعلى حد
and mitigate the risks
وتقليل المخاطر
of living on a planet that's driven by only two processes,
بالعيش على كوكب تقوده عمليتان فقط
two sources of energy,
مصدران للطاقة
one of which is solar,
أحداهما الشمسية
that drives the winds, the waves,
التي تحرك الرياح والأمواج
the clouds, the storms and photosynthesis.
والسحب والعواصف والتركيب الضوئي
The second one is internal energy.
والثانية هي الطاقة الداخلية
And these two war against one another
وهاتان الطاقتان تتحاربان ضد بعض
almost continuously.
دائما تقريبا
Mountain ranges, plate tectonics,
السلاسل الجبلية, والصفائح التكتونية
moves the continents around, forms ore deposits.
تحرك القارات, تشكل مستودعات الخام
Volcanoes erupt.
تثور البراكين
That's the planet that we live on.
هذا هو الكوكب الذي نعيش عليه
It's immensely complex.
إنه معقد بشكل هائل
Now I don't expect all of you to see all the details here,
والآن لا أعتقد أنكم جميعا ستشاهدون التفاصيل هنا
but what I want you to see is
لكن ما أريدكم أن تروه
this is about 10 percent
هذه حوالي عشرة بالمئة
of the processes that operate within
من العمليات التي تحدث داخل
the oceans almost continuously,
المحيطات بشكل شبه دائم
and have for the last 4 billion years.
واستمرت منذ أربعة مليارات سنة
This is a system that's been around a very long time.
هذا نظام مستمرفي العمل منذ فترة طويلة جدا
And these have all co-evolved.
وكل هذه شاركت في التطور
What do I mean by that?
مالذي أقصده بهذا؟
They interact with one another constantly.
أنهم يتفاعلون مع بعضهم دائما
All of them interact with one another.
كلهم يتفاعلون مع بعضهم
So the complexity of this system that we're looking at,
إذاً تعقيد هذا النظام الذي نشاهده ,
the one driven by the sun --
الذي قادته الشمس--
upper portion, mostly --
معظم الجزء العلوي
and the lower portion is partly driven
والجزء السفلي تقوده جزئيا
by the input from heat below
الحرارة المدخلة من الأسفل
and by other processes.
وعمليات أخرى
This is very, very important
هذا مهم للغاية
because this is the system, this is the crucible,
لأنه هذا هو النظام, هذه هي البوتقة
out of which life on the planet came,
التي منها ظهرت الحياة على الكوكب
and it's now time for us to understand it.
وآن الوقت لنا لفهمها
We must understand it.
يجب أن نفهمها
That's one of the themes that Sylvia reminds us about:
هذه إحدى السمات التي تذكرنا بها سيلفيا
understand this ocean of ours,
فهم المحيط الذي يخصنا
this basic life support system,
نظام دعم الحياة الأساسي هذا
the dominant life support system on the planet.
نظام دعم الحياة المسيطر على هذا الكوكب
Look at this complexity here.
إنظروا لهذا التعقيد هنا
This is only one variable.
هذا مجرد متغير واحد
If you can see the complexity,
إن إستطعتم رؤية هذا التعقيد
you can see how
لرأيتم كيف
tiny, little eddies
دوامات صغيرة جدا
and large eddies and the motion --
ودوامات كبيرة والحركة
this is just sea surface temperature,
هذه فقط درجة حرارة سطح البحر
but it's immensely complicated.
لكنها معقدة بشكل هائل
Now a layer in,
وبإضافة طبقات
the other two or three hundred processes
المئتان أو الثلاثمئة عملية أخرى
that are all interacting,
المتفاعلة معا جميعا
partly as a function of temperature, partly as a function of all the other factors,
جزئيا كعملية للحرارة, وجزئيا كعملية لكل العوامل الأخرى
and you've got a really complicated system.
وتجدون نظاما معقدا جدا
That's our challenge, is to understand,
هذا هو تحدينا أن نفهم
understand this system in new and phenomenal ways.
نفهم النظام وطرق الظواهر
And there's an urgency to this.
وهناك ضرورة ملحة لذلك
Part of the urgency comes from the fact
جزء من هذه الضرورة ياتي من حقيقة
that, of order, a billion people on the planet currently
أنه خارج النظام يوجد مليار شخص على الكوكب حاليا
are undernourished or starving.
ضعيف التغذية أو يتضور جوعا
And part of the issue
وجزء من المسألة
is for Cody --
بالنسبة لكودي--
who's here,
الذي هو هنا
16 years old --
وعمره ستة عشر عاما
and I have permission to relay this number.
وعندي التصريح لتبديل هذا الرقم
When he, 40 years from now,
أنه, بعد أربعين عاما من الآن,
is the age of Nancy Brown,
بعمر نانسي براون,
there are going to be
سيكون هناك
another two and a half billion people on the planet.
مليارين ونصف شخص آخر على الكوكب
We can't solve all the problems
لن نستطيع حل جميع المشكلات
by looking only at the oceans,
بالبحث فقط في المحيط
but if we don't understand
لكننا إذا لم نفهم
the fundamental life support system of this planet
نظام دعم الحياة الأساسي لهذا الكوكب
much more thoroughly than we do now,
بشكل شامل أكثر مما نفهمه الآن
then the stresses that we will face,
عندئذ تكون الضغوط التي سنواجهها
and that Cody will face,
والتي سيواجهها كودي
and even Nancy, who's going to live till she's 98,
وحتى نانسي التي ستعيش حتى ثمانية وتسعون عاما
will have really problems coping.
سنواجه مشاكل حقيقية في التأقلم
All right, let's talk about another perspective
حسنا, لنتحدث عن وجهة نظر أخرى
on the importance of the oceans.
عن أهمية المحيطات
Look at this diagram, which is showing
انظروا الى الرسم البياني هذا, الذي يبين
warm waters in red,
المياه الدافئة باللون الأحمر
cool waters in blue,
المياة الباردة باللون الأزرق
and on the continents, what you're seeing in bright green,
وعلى القارات, ما ترونه بالون الأخضر الفاتح
is the growth of vegetation,
يمثّل نمو النباتات
and in olive green, the dieback of vegetation.
وباللون الأخضر الزيتوني, إنحسار نمو النباتات
And in the lower left hand corner there's a clock ticking away
وفي الركن الأسفل الأيسر توجد ساعة تمضي
from 1982 to 1998
منذ العام 1982 حتى العام 1998
and then cycling again.
وتعود لتدور مجددا
What you'll see is that the rhythms
ما الذي سترونه هو أن النغمات
of growth, of vegetation --
في النمو, في نمو النباتات--
a subset of which is food on the continents --
التي يعتبر الطعام قائمة فرعية منه على القارات
is directly tied to the rhythms
مرتبطة مباشرة لنغمات
of the sea surface temperatures.
لحرارة سطح البحر
The oceans control,
إن المحيطات تتحكم
or at least significantly influence,
أو على الأقل تؤثر بشدة
correlate with,
مرتبطة مع
the growth patterns and the drought patterns
أنماط النمو وأنماط الجفاف
and the rain patterns on the continents.
وأنماط الأمطار على القارات
So people in Kansas, in a wheat field in Kansas,
إذاً فالناس في كانساس, في حقل قمح في كانساس
need to understand that the oceans
يجب أن يفهموا أن المحيطات
are central to them as well.
هي مركزية لهم أيضا
Another complexity: this is the age of the oceans.
تعقيد آخر: هذا هو عمر المحيطات
I'm going to layer in on top of this
سأضع فوق هذا طبقة
the tectonic plates.
الصفائح التكتونية
The age of the ocean, the tectonic plates,
عمر المحيط , والصفائح التكتونية
gives rise to a totally new phenomenon
تظهر ظاهرة جديدة كليا
that we have heard about
سمعنا عنها
in this conference.
في هذا المؤتمر
And I share with you some very high-definition video
وأشارك معكم بعض الفيديوهات فائقة الجودة
that we collected in real time.
التي جمعناها في الزمن الحقيقي (مباشرة)
Seconds after this video was taken,
بعد ثوان من أخذ هذا الفيديو
people in Beijing,
أناس في بكين
people in Sydney, people in Amsterdam,
وأناس في سيدني, وأناس في أمستردام
people in Washington D.C. were watching this.
وأناس في واشنطون العاصمة كانو يشاهدون هذا
Now you've heard of hydrothermal vents,
الآن قد سمعتم بشقوق الماء الهيدروحرارية (الساخنة)
but the other discovery
لكن الإكتشاف الآخر
is that deep below the sea floor,
أنه في العمق تحت قاع البحر
there is vast reservoir of microbial activity,
يوجد مستودع هائل للنشاط الجرثومي (الميكروبي)
which we have only just discovered
الذي إكتشفناه لتونا
and we have almost no way to study.
والذي قد لا يكون لنا أية طريقة لدراسته
Some people have estimated
بعض الناس قدروا
that the biomass
أن الكتلة الحية
tied up in these microbes
المرتبطة بتلك الميكروبات
living in the pours and the cracks
التي تعيش في المصبات والشقوق
of the sea floor and below
في قاع البحر وأسفل منه
rival the total amount of living biomass
تعادل مجموع الكتلة الحية
at the surface of the planet.
على سطح الكوكب
It's an astonishing insight,
إنها لمحة مذهلة
and we have only found out about this recently.
وقد عرفنا عنها مؤخرا فقط
This is very, very exciting.
إنه مثير جدا
It may be the next rainforest,
قد تكون الغابة المطيرة القادمة
in terms of pharmaceuticals.
في المصطلح الصيدلاني
We know little or nothing about it.
نعرف القليل أو لاشيء عنها
Well, Marcel Proust has this wonderful saying
حسنا, لدى مارسيل بروست هذة المقولة الجميلة
that, "The real voyage of discovery
"الرحلة الحقيقية للإستكشاف
consists not so much in seeking new territory,
لا تتكون بشكل كيبرمن البحث عن مناطق جديدة
but possibly in having new sets of eyes,"
ولكن بإمكانية الحصول على أعين جديدة"
new ways of seeing things,
طرق جديدة لرؤية الأشياء
a new mindset.
عقل جديد
And many of you remember
كثير منكم يتذكروا
the early stages of oceanography,
المراحل الأولية لعلم المحيطات,
when we had to use what we had at our fingertips.
عندما كنا مضطرين لإستخدام ما في متناول أيدينا
And it wasn't easy. It wasn't easy in those days.
ولم يكن الأمر سهلا. لم يكن سهلا تلك الأيام
Some of you remember this, I'm sure.
بعضكم يتذكر هذا, إنني متأكد
And now, we have an entire suite of tools
والآن, أصبحنا نمتلك طقما كاملا من المعدات
that are really pretty powerful --
التي هي حقا قوية
ships, satellites, moorings.
بواخر, أقمار صناعية, مراسي
But they don't quite cut it. They don't quite give us what we need.
ولكنها لا تنجز المهمة تماما. لا تعطينا ما نحتاجه تماما
And the program that I wanted to talk to you about
والبرنامج الذي أردت أن أحدثكم عنه
just a little bit here,
بشكل بسيط هنا
was funded, and it involves autonomous vehicles
تم تمويله, وقد تضمن آليات مستقلة
like the one running across the base of this image.
كتلك التي تمر عبر أسفل الصورة
Modeling: on the right hand side,
النمذجة: على الجانب الأيمن
there's a very complex computational model.
نموذج محوسب مركب
On the left hand side, there's a new type of mooring,
على الجانب الأيسر, يوجد نوع جديد من المراسي
which I'll show you in just a second.
التي سأوضحها بعد قليل
And on the basis
وعلى القواعد
of several points,
لعدة نقاط,
the oceans are complex, and they're central to the life on earth.
المحيطات معقدة, وهي مركزية للحياة على الأرض
They are changing rapidly, but not predictably.
وهي تتغير سريعا, ولكن بشكل لايمكن التنبؤ به
And the models that we need to predict the future
والنماذج التي نحتاجها للتنبؤ بالمستقبل
do not have enough data to refine them.
لا تمتلك البيانات الكافية لتصقلها
The computational power
الطاقة الحاسوبية
is amazing.
مدهشة
But without data, those models
لكن دون البيانات, هذه النماذج
will never ever be predicted.
لن يتنبأ بها أبدا
And that's what we really need.
وهذا هو ما نحتاجه حقا
For a variety of reasons they're dangerous,
لأسباب متعددة هي خطيرة
but we feel that OOI,
لكننا نحس أن مبادرة مرصد المحيط (OOI),
this Ocean Observatory Initiative,
مبادرة مرصد المحيط هذه
which the National Science Foundation
التي قامت منظمة العلوم الوطنية
has begun to fund,
بالبدء في إنشائها
has the potential to really transform things.
تمتلك إمكانية تحويل الأشياء حقا
And the goal of the program is to
والهدف من هذا البرنامج هو
launch an era of scientific discovery
الإنطلاق بعصر من الإستكشاف العلمي
and understanding
والفهم
across and within the ocean basins,
عبر وداخل أحواض المحيطات
utilizing widely accessible,
موظفة محاضرات
interactive telepresence.
تفاعلية عن بُعد وذات إمكانية وصول واسعة
It's a new world.
إنه عالم جديد
We will be present throughout
سنكون حاضرين عبر
the volume of the ocean, at will,
كتلة المحيط, إن رغبنا بذلك
communicating in real time.
متصلين معا مباشرة
And this is what the system involves,
وهذا هو ما يتضمنه النظام
a number of sites in the southern hemisphere,
مجموعة من المواقع في نصف الكرة الأرضية الجنوبي
shown in those circles.
الظاهرة في تلك الدوائر
And in the northern hemisphere there are four sites.
وفي نصف الكرة الأرضية الشمالي توجد أربعة مواقع
I won't talk a lot about most of them right here,
لن أتحدث كثيرا عن معظمها هنا
but the one on the west coast, that's in the box,
ولكن الموقع الذي على الساحل الغربي, ذلك الذي في المربع
is called the regional scale nodes.
يدعى روابط المقياس المحلي
It was once called Neptune.
وكان يدعى نبتون سابقا
And let me show you what's behind it.
ودعوني أريكم ماذا خلفه
Fiber: next-generation way of communicating.
ألياف ضوئية, طريقة الجيل التالي للإتصال
You can see the copper tips on these things.
ترون الأطراف النحاسية على هذه الأشياء
You can transmit power,
يمكنكم نقل الطاقة
but the bandwidth is in those tiny, little threads
لكن السعة الموجية في تلك الخيوط الصغيرة جدا
smaller than the hair on your head in diameter.
أصغر من شعر رؤوسكم في الُقطر
And this particular set here
وهذا الطقم المحدد هنا
can transmit something of the order of
يستطيع نقل ما يقارب
three to five terabits per second.
ثلاثة إلى خمسة تيرابيت في الثانية
This is phenomenal bandwidth.
هذه السعة الموجية ظاهرة
And this is what the planet looks like.
وهذا هو ما يبدو عليه الكوكب
We are already laced up
قد ربطنا بالفعل
as if we're in a fiber optic corset, if you like.
بالألياف الضوئية مشدات إن أردتم
This is what it looks like.
هذا ما يبدو عليه
And the cables go really continent to continent.
والكابلات تمر حقا من قارة لأخرى
It's a very powerful system,
إنه نظام قوي جدا
and most of our communications consist of it.
ومعظم إتصالاتنا تتكون منه
So this is the system that I'm talking about,
إذاً هذا هو النظام الذي أتحدث عنه
off the west coast. It's coincident with the tectonic plate,
من الساحل الغربي – متوافقا مع الصفيحة التكتونية
the Juan de Fuca tectonic plate.
صفيحة خوان دي فوكا التكتونية
And it's going to deliver abundant power
والتي ستوفر طاقة بغزرة
and unprecedented bandwidth
وسعة موجية غير معهودة
across this entire volume --
عبر كل هذه الكتلة--
in the overlying ocean,
في المحيط الجاسم فوقها,
on the sea floor and below the sea floor.
على قاع البحر وأسفل من قاع البحر
Bandwidth and power
السعة الموجية والطاقة
and a wide variety of processes
ومجموعة عمليات واسعة التعدد
that will be operating.
التي ستشتغل
This is what one of those primary nodes looks like,
هذا هو ما تبدو عليه إحدى تلك الروابط الأساسية
and it's like a sub station with power and bandwidth
وهي كمحطة فرعية مع طاقة وسعة موجية
that can spread out over an area the size of Seattle.
تستطيع الإنتشار فوق مساحة بحجم سياتل
And the kind of science that can be done
ونوع العلوم التي يمكن عملها
will be determined by a variety of scientists who want to be involved
ستحدد من مجموعة متعددة من العلماء يريدون أن ينضموا
and can bring the instrumentation to the table.
ويستطيعون إستخدام الآلات على أرض الواقع
They will bring it and link it in.
سيأتون بها ويوصلونها
It'll be, in a sense, like having time on a telescope,
ستكون مثل الحصول على الوقت على تلسكوب
except you'll have your own port.
بإستثناء إنه ستكون لك بوابة منفصلة
Climate change, ocean acidification,
التغير المناخي, تحمض المحيط
dissolved oxygen,
الأكسجين المذاب
carbon cycle, coastal upwelling,
الدورة الكربونية, تغير المياه على السواحل
fishing dynamics --
تحركات الأسماك
the full spectrum of
كل طيف
earth science and ocean science
علم الأرض وعلم المحيط
simultaneously in the same volume.
لحظيا على نفس الكتلة
So anyone coming along later
فيتمكن أي شخص يأتي لاحقا
simply accesses the database
ببساطة الولوج لقاعدة البيانات
and can draw down the information they need
ويستطيع جلب المعلومات التي يحتاج إليها
about anything that has taken place.
تقريبا كل ما حدث
And this is just the first of these.
وهذا هو أول هذه الأشياء فقط
In conjunction with our Canadian colleagues, we've set this up.
بالإقتران مع زملائنا الكنديين, أنشأنا هذا
Now I want to take you into the caldera.
والآن أريد أن آخذكم للإنهيار البركاني
On the left hand side there
على الناحية اليسرى هنا
is a large volcano called Axial Seamount.
يوجد بركان كبير يدعى آكسيال سيماونت
And we're going to go down into the Axial Seamount
ونحن سندخل إلى داخل آكسيال سيماونت
using animation.
بإستخدام الرسوم المتحركة
Here's what this system is going to look like
هذا ما سيبدو عليه النظام
that we are funded to build at this point.
الذي مولنا لبنائه حتى هذه النقطة
Very powerful.
قوي جدا
That's an elevator that's constantly moving up and down,
هذا مصعد يتحرك دائما للأعلى والأسفل
but it can be controlled by the folks on land
ولكن يمكن التحكم به بالأشخاص على الأرض
who are responsible for it.
المسئولين عنه
Or they can transfer control
ويمكنهم نقل التحكم
to someone in India or China
لشخص ما في الهند أو الصين
who can take over for a while,
يمكنه أن يحل في التحكم لفترة
because it's all going to be directly connected
لأنه سيكون كله متصل مباشرة
through the Internet.
عبر الإنترنت
There will be massive amounts of data flowing ashore,
سيكون هناك فيض كمي هائل من البيانات
all available to anyone who has any interest in using it.
كله متاح لأي شخص يملك أي رغبة في إستخدامه
This is going to be much more powerful
سيكون هذا أقوى بكثير
than having a single ship
من الحصول على باخرة واحدة
in a single location,
في موقع واحد
then move to a new location.
ثم التحرك الى موقع جديد
We're flying across the caldera floor.
نحن نطير عبر أرضية الإنهيار البركاني
There is a number of robotic systems.
هناك عدد من الأنظمة الروبوتية
There's cameras that can be turned on and off at your will,
هناك كاميرات يمكن تشغيلها وأيقافها برغبتكم
if those are your experiments.
إن كانت تلك تجاربكم
The kinds of systems that will be down there,
نوع الأنظمة التي ستكون بالأسفل هناك
the kinds of instruments that will be on the sea floor,
نوع الآليات التي ستكون على قاع البحر
consist of -- if you can read them there --
تتكون من – إن إستطعتم قرائتها هناك
there's cameras, there's pressure sensors,
هناك كاميرات, حساسات ضغط
fluorometers, there's seismometers.
أدوات قياس الضوء, هناك أدوات قياس التحرك
It's a full spectrum of tools.
إنها سلسلة كاملة من الأدوات
Now, that mound right there
والآن, هذه الربوة هناك
actually looks like this.
تبدو في الحقيقة هكذا
This is what it actually looks like.
هذا ما تبدو عليه حقيقة
And this is the kind of activity
وهذا النوع من النشاطات
that we can see with high-definition video,
التي نستطيع مشاهدتها بفيديو شديد الوضوح
because the bandwidth of these cables
لأن السعة الموجية لهذه الكابلات
is so huge
هائلة
that we could have five to 10
لدرجة أننا نستطيع تشغيل من خمسة الى عشرة
stereo HD systems
أنظمة التصويرالستيريو (الصوتية) HD
running continuously
تعمل دائما
and, again, directed through robotic techniques from land.
وأيضا, تدارعبر تقنيات روبوتية من الأرض
Very, very powerful.
قوي جدا, جدا
And these are the things that we're funded to do today.
وهذه هي الأشياء التي تم تمويلنا لإنشائها اليوم
So what can we actually do tomorrow?
إذاً ما الذي نستطيع عمله في الغد؟
We're about to ride the wave
نحن على وشك أن نركب موجة
of technological opportunity.
من الإمكانات التكنولوجية
There are emerging technologies throughout
هنك تكنولوجيا ناشئة من
the field around oceanography,
حول مجال علم المحيطات
which we will incorporate into oceanography,
سنشركها في علم المحيطات
and through that convergence,
ومن هذا التلاقي
we will transform oceanography into something even more magical.
سنحول علم المحيطات لشيء أكثر سحرا مما هو عليه
Robotics systems are just incredible these days,
الأنظمة الروبوتية أصبحت مذهلة هذه الأيام
absolutely incredible.
مذهلة تماما
And we will be bringing robotics of all sorts
ونحن نجلب الروبوتية بكل أنواعها
into the ocean.
إلى داخل المحيط
Nanotechnology: this is a small generator.
تكنولوجيا النانو(فائقة الصغر) : هذا مولد طاقة صغير
It's smaller than a postage stamp,
أصغر من طابع البريد
and it can generate power just by being
ويستطيع توليد الطاقة فقط من كونه
attached to your shirt as you move.
معلقا بقميصك بينما تتحرك
Just as you move, it generates power.
بمجرد تحركك, ينتج الطاقة
There are many kinds of things that can be used in the ocean, continuously.
هناك العديد من أنواع الأشياء التي يمكن إستخدامها في المحيط, دائما
Imaging: Many of you know a good deal more about this type of thing than I,
التصوير: الكثير منكم يعرفون عن هذا النوع من الأشياء أكثر مني
but stereo imaging at four times the definition
لكن التصوير الاستريو (الصوتي) أدق أكثر بأربعة مرات
that we have in HD
مما نحصل عليه ب الجودة الفائقة HD
will be routine within five years.
ستكون معتادة خلال خمس سنوات
And this is the magic one.
وهذه هي السحرية
As a result of the human genome process,
كنتيجة لعملية الجينات البشرية
we are in a situation where
نحن في وضعية تمكننا من
events that take place in the ocean --
مراقبة الأحداث التي تحدث في المحيط
like an erupting volcano, or something of that sort --
كثورة بركان, أو شيء من هذا القبيل--
can actually be sampled.
يمكن حقا أن تعاين
We pump the fluid through one of these systems,
نضخ السائل عبر أحد هذه الأنظمة,
and we press the button,
ونضغط على الزر,
and it's analyzed for the genomic character.
ويتم تحليله لمعرفة صفاته الجينية
And that's transmitted back to land immediately.
وهذا ينقل للأرض مباشرة
So in the volume of the ocean,
حيث أنه في كتلة المحيط
we will know, not just the physics and the chemistry,
سنعرف, ليس فقط الفيزياء والكيمياء
but the base of the food chain
ولكن قاعدة السلسلة الغذائية
will be transparent to us
ستكون شفافة لنا
with data on a continuous basis.
بالبيانات بشكل مستمر
Grid computing: the power of grid computers
الحوسبة الشبكية: قدرة الحواسيب الشبكية
is going to be just amazing here.
ستكون أروع ما يكون هنا
We will soon be using grid computing
سنستخدم قريبا الحوسبة الشبكية
to do pretty much everything, like adjust the data
لعمل كل شيء تقريبا, كتعديل البيانات
and everything
وكل شيء
that goes with the data.
يأتي مع البيانات
The power generation will come from the ocean itself.
إنتاج الطاقة سيأتي من المحيط نفسه
And the next generation fiber
والجيل القادم من الألياف
will be simply magic.
سيكون ببساطة سحريا
It's far beyond what we currently have.
إنه أبعد بكثير مما نملك حاليا
So the presence of the power
فبوجود الطاقة
and the bandwidth in the environment
والسعة الموجية في البيئة
will allow all of these new technologies
ستسمح لكل هذه التكنولوجيا الجديدة
to converge in a manner that is just unprecedented.
لتلتقي بشكل لم يكن له مثيل قبلا
So within five to seven years,
إذاً خلال خمسة إلى سبعة سنوات من الآن
I see us having
أرى أننا نملك
a capacity to be completely present
أهلية أن نكون حاضرين تماما
throughout the ocean
عبر المحيط
and have all of that connected to the Internet,
وبربط هذا كله بالإنترنت
so we can reach many, many folks.
بإمكاننا أن نتصل بالعديد والعديد من الأشخاص
Delivering the power and the bandwidth into the ocean
بتوصيل الطاقة والسعة الموجية إلى المحيط
will dramatically accelerate adaptation.
ستسرع التقبل بشكل هائل
Here's an example.
مثال لذلك
When earthquakes take place, massive amounts
عند حدوث هزة أرضية, كميات هائلة
of these new microbes we've never seen before
من الميكروبات الجديدة التي لم نرها من قبل
come out of the sea floor.
تخرج من قاع البحر
We have a way of addressing that,
لدينا طريق لمواجهة ذلك
a new way of addressing that.
طريق جديدة لمواجهة ذلك
We've determined from the earthquake activity that you're seeing here
حددنا من نشاط الهزة الأرضية التي ترونها هنا
that the top of that volcano is erupting,
أن قمة هذا البركان تثور
so we deploy the troops.
فننشر كشافتنا
What are the troops? The troops are the autonomous vehicles, of course.
ما هي الكشافة؟ الكشافة آلات مستقلة, طبعا
And they fly into the erupting volcano.
وهي تسرع إلى البركان الثائر
They sample the fluids coming out of the sea floor
تأخذ عينة من السوائل الخارجة من قاع البحر
during an eruption,
أثناء الثوران
which have the microbes that have never been
التي تحوي الميكروبات التي لم يحدث من قبل
to the surface of the planet before.
أن كانت على سطح الكوكب
They eject it to the surface where it floats,
تطلقها نحو السطح حيث تطفو
and it is picked up
وتلتقطها
by an autonomous airplane,
طائرات مستقلة
and it's brought back to the laboratory
وتجلبها عائدة إلى المختبر
within 24 hours of the eruption.
خلال 24 ساعة من حدوث الثوران
This is doable. All the pieces are there.
هذا يمكن عمله كل القطع موجودة هنا
A laboratory: many of you heard what happened
مختبر: الكثير منكم سمع بما حدث
on 9/7.
في 7/9
Some doctors in New York City removed
قام بعض الأطباء في نيويورك بإستئصال
the gallbladder of a woman in France.
المرارة لامرأة في فرنسا
We could do work on the sea floor that would be stunning,
نستطيع القيام بأعمال في قاع البحر ستكون صاعقة
and it would be on live TV,
وستكون على التلفاز مباشرة
if we have interesting things to show.
لو كان لنا أشياء مثيرة لعرضها
So we can bring an entirely new telepresence
سنأتي بجلسات حضور عن بعد جديدة كليا
to the world, throughout the ocean.
إلى العالم من المحيط
This -- I've shown you sea floor --
هذا— أريتكم قاع البحر
but so the goal here is real time interaction
لكن الهدف هنا هو تفاعلات الزمن الحقيقي
with the oceans from anywhere on earth.
مع المحيطات في أي مكان في العالم
It's going to be amazing.
ستكون مثيرة
And as I go here,
وبينما أمضي هنا,
I just want to show you what we can bring into classrooms,
أريد فقط أن نشاهد ما الذي يمكن جلبه للفصول الدراسية
and indeed, what we can bring into your pocket.
وبالتأكيد ما الذي يمكننا جلبه لجيبك
Many of you don't think of this yet,
الكثير منكم لا يفكر بهذا الآن
but the ocean will be in your pocket.
لكن المحيط سيكون في جيبكم
It won't be long. It won't be long.
لن يكون بعيدا. لن يكون بعيدا
So let me leave you then
إذاً دعوني أترككم بعد ذلك
with a few words
مع بعض الكلمات
from another poet, if you'll forgive me.
من شاعر آخر, إن عذرتموني
In 1943,
في عام 1943
T.S. Eliot wrote the "Four Quartets."
كتب تي. إس. إليوت ال "رباعيات الأربع"
He won the Nobel Prize for literature
وفاز بجائزة نوبل للآداب
in 1948.
في عام 1948
In "Little Gidding" he says --
في "جيدينج الصغيرة" يقول
speaking I think for the human race,
متحدثا فيما أعتقد للعرق البشري
but certainly for the TED Conference and Sylvia --
وبالتأكيد لمؤتمر تيد ولسيلفيا
"We shall not cease from exploration,
"يجب أن لا نتوقف عن الإستكشاف
and the end of all our exploring
وفي نهاية كل إستكشافنا
will be to arrive where we started
ستكون بالوصول لحيث بدأنا
and know the place for the first time,
ومعرفة المكان لأول مرة
arrive through the unknown remembered gate
الوصول عبر بوابة مجهولة متذكرة
where the last of earth left to discover
حيث نهاية العالم بقيت لتكتشف
is that which was the beginning.
هي التي كانت منها البداية
At the source of the longest river
في منبع النهر الأطول
the voice of a hidden waterfall
صوت شلال مخفي
not known because not looked for,
لم يعرف لأنه لم يبحث عنه
but heard, half heard
ولكن سمع, نصف إستماع
in the stillness beneath the waves of the sea."
في الجمود تحت أمواج البحر"
Thank you.
شكرا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)